בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is פ"ד, Pei Dalet, and
we've hit in the middle of a large aggadic section of the
גמרא, Gemara, maybe somebody felt
we were
up for it with all of the hard halachic stuff we've been
doing until now. And we are in the middle of a story
since the גמרא Gemara talk about workers and what time they get
up and getting up early and so on, we have turned into
a story of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon that
was encountered somebody, a Jew presumably, who was appointed by the king
to catch Jewish thieves. And he was giving him advice on how
to do that based on who was nodding off at the tavern
during lunchtime, again getting to this question of what time workers are
getting up, and then he was given the assignment to be the
policeman by the king. The king said, "Oh, you know what you're
doing, you take the assignment." Okay, and we'll pick up maybe where
it says about fifteen lines from the bottom, we'll quickly re-read this
part. Fifteen lines before the lines get wide. The line starts with
the word אמרו. amru. So it says אמרו, amru, they said: קריינא
דאיגרתא איהו ליהוי פרונקא. karyana de-igarta ihu leihavei parvanka. Oh, the reader
of the letter, he should be the reader of the proclamation, should
be the one that carries it out. So if you know what
you're doing, you be the policeman. אותיבו ashivu לרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון.
le-Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon. Okay, so they basically brought forward רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon, they assigned him to be the
policeman, דקא תפיס גנבי, de-katafis ganvei, and he now had to catch
the thieves, the Jewish thieves. ושדר ליה רבי יהושע בן קרחה. ve-shadar
leih Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. So רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha sent to him: חומץ בן יין. chomets ben yayin. Vinegar,
the son of wine, meaning you're a disappointment to your father. I'm
sorry, where were we? The line starts with the word חומץ, chomets,
it's about fifteen lines before the lines get wide on פ"ג עמוד
ב. Pei Gimel Amud Bet. חומץ בן יין, chomets ben yayin, vinegar
the son of wine, עד מתי אתה מוסר עמו של אלהינו להריגה?
ad matay ata moser amei shel eloheinu la-hariga? How long will you
be giving over our people to be executed? Right, a גנב ganav
would be executed. You're being a Jewish king catching Jewish thieves, or
a Jewish policeman catching Jewish thieves for the non-Jewish king. What are
you doing participating in the government like this? Which raises obviously important
questions nowadays, right? Being a policeman, being a prosecutor, etc. So the
גמרא Gemara says: שלח ליה, shalach leih, he sent back to him:
קוצים אני מכלה מן הכרם. kotzim ani mechaleh min hakerem. No, I'm
doing necessary work, I'm getting rid of the thorns from the vineyard.
You know, these people are trouble within our nation. Now, of course,
how does that allow you to get them executed is a different
question. שלח ליה, shalach leih, so he sent back to him: יבוא
בעל הכרם ויכלה את קוציו. yavo ba'al hakerem ve-yechaleh et kotzav. Let
the owner of the vineyard come and get rid of his own
thorns. That's not your responsibility, and especially given in this context in
which the consequence is very harsh, obviously much harsher than הלכה Halacha
would assign to these people. Okay, so there's no real resolution to
that. I don't know. יומא חד פגע ביה ההוא כובס, yoma chad
paga beih hahu kovas, still not the same level of evidence. יומא
חד פגע ביה ההוא כובס. yoma chad paga beih hahu kovas. Okay,
so a certain day, maybe because he had been called this by
רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, this word was getting
around, even before social media. So, so a certain
launderer bumped into him, to this great rabbi, right? That means he
might have been insulted by רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Korcha, but nevertheless רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon was
a great rabbi. קרי ליה חומץ בן יין, kari leih chomets ben
yayin, and he called him vinegar son of wine. So, you know,
so that name label had stuck and now even this like very
this commoner was calling him this. אמר, amar, so רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon said: מדי חציף כולי האי, midei-chatzif kulei
hai,
if he could be so, have so much חוצפה, chutzpah, have so
much temerity to call me that that, שמע מינה רשע הוא. shema
mina rasha hi. He must be that he's a רשע, rasha, he
must be that he's evil in other ways. אמר להו ותפסוהו. amar
lehu ve-tafsuhu. So he said to his, you know, his policemen, he
said to the people he was working with, and his deputies or
whatever, and they seized him. Okay, so because now of course here
becomes exactly part of the challenge, which is once you have power,
right, how can you abuse it even if you're trying to do
the right thing? In his own mind he said oh no, this
guy must be a גנב ganav or whatever. But of course he
had just been insulted by this guy, right? So this actually shows
some of the danger of this even if you think and you're
trying to do the right thing. אמר להו ותפסוהו, amar lehu ve-tafsuhu,
I'm sorry,
he said to his deputies grab him, תפסוהו tafsuhu and they seized
him. לבתר דנח דעתיה, le-vatar denach daateih,
after his mind was set at ease, like okay after he calmed
down a bit, which again shows that he was very obviously he
was acting under anger and at a stage of upset and so
on and he managed to rationalize certain, you know, to assume certain
things, but then he calmed down and he realized he had acted
rashly. אזל בתריה לפרוקיה, azal batreih le-farukei, he went after him to
try to redeem him. Right, now that he had been seized by
the government, okay, it wasn't under his control anymore. So now he
was trying to see if he could get him out of jail,
okay, or get him out of the execution that was awaiting him.
ולא מצי, ve-lo matzi, and he wasn't able to. And קרא עליה:
kara aleih: שומר פיו ולשונו שומר מצרות נפשו. shomer piv u-leshono shomer
mi-tsarot nafsho.
Now who's the עליה? aleih? רש"י Rashi says it means that he
proclaimed about this person that had been seized, the one who guards
his mouth and his tongue will protect himself from anguish. So that
you know you shouldn't have like it's because he called me vinegar
the son of wine that that's if he had been kept quiet
this wouldn't have happened. Of course he might have been talking about
himself, right? If I had kept myself quiet and I hadn't been
watching what I said, then that... and and what and did not
speak rashly then this wouldn't have happened. Okay. זקפו. Zakfu. So they
basically crucified him, they hung him up, they strung him up. I
don't know if it means crucified, they strung him up. Okay, if
this, I mean, if this was the Persian government, it wouldn't have
been crucified. Come to see זקיפא, Zikifa, he stood underneath where he
had been strung up, דקא בכי de-ka bakhi and he was crying.
אמרו ליה, Amru lei, רבי, Rabbi, so people said to him, you
know, רבי, Rabbi, אל ירע בעיניך, al ye-ra be-einecha, do not make...
don't, don't feel so, you know, so much blame, don't blame yourself
too much about this, you know, the guy was, you were right,
this guy really was a רשע. Rasha. Don't think you killed an
innocent man. Okay, שהוא ובנו באו על נערה מאורסה ביום הכיפורים. she-hu
u-veno ba-u al na-ara me-orasa be-Yom Ha-Kippurim.
Just to show you how wicked he was, he together with his
son had sex with a woman who was betrothed to another man
on Yom Kippur, right, how much worse could you do than that?
Okay. So he was a total רשע. Rasha. Right. So הניח ידו
על בני מעיו, hiniach yado al benei me-av,
and all those things are like חייב מיתה, chayav mita, right? Well,
I mean having sex on Yom Kippur isn't, but sex with an
נערה מאורסה na-ara me-orasa is. It could have been worse. הניח ידו
על בני מעיו, hiniach yado al benei me-av, he put his hands
on his belly, on his stomach, and we're going to find out
in a minute that he was very... he was obese. Portly, thank
you. אמרו, Amru, שישו בני מעיי שישו, Sisu benei me-ai sisu, rejoice
my innards, rejoice. ומה, U-mah, because מספיקא שלכם כך, masfeika shelachem kach,
things that you're uncertain turns out to be this way, that even
I wasn't certain, I thought he was a רשע Rasha but obviously
I didn't have any good strong evidence, you know, and nevertheless it
turns out that I was right, ודאי
שלכם על אחת כמה וכמה, vada-i shelachem al achat kamma ve-kamma, how
much more the things you are certain about. You know, this is
sort of talking about the sense that, like, you know, like when
we sort of said, like, you know, when we intuit something, you
know, do we say it comes from our heart, do we say
it comes from our mind, you know, where do we think thought
and intuition, you know, comes from? So here they often have a
sense of like coming from, like for instance they'd say, like, you
know, I have a gut, I have a gut feeling, right? The
gut, that's the gut, right? Sometimes actually when פוסקים poskim are talking
about, you know, about a certain פסק psak and they don't have
any textual evidence, they say, אומר אני מסברת הכרס, omer ani mi-sevarat
ha-kares, I say from the, from the thinking of my gut. Okay,
like my gut feeling about this, you know, I don't have any
textual proof but this is like a gut instinct around this. Okay,
so anyway so it's interesting he sort of seeing his gut as
the source of this intuition. Okay, so ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, I
was right. And it all tells, everything's telling. Yeah, but it's, but
he's not going to be satisfied. I mean, he's trying to persuade
himself that it's all okay, but nevertheless, okay, so let's keep on
reading. Okay, second wide line here at the bottom. So he says,
ודאי שלכם על אחת כמה וכמה, vada-i shelachem al achat kamma ve-kamma,
מובטח אני בכם, muftach ani bachem, I am confident in you, my
gut here, you know, שאין רימה ותולעה שולטת בכם, she-ein rimma ve-tole-ah
sholetet bachem, that no worm or, you know, maggot will have dominion
over you at the day of death, you know, because you're so
pure, my gut, like it's so, you know, it's so right. ואפילו
הכי, Va-afilu hakhi, even though he said this to himself, לא מיתבא
דעתיה, lo mityashev da-atei,
so he was not... his mind was not put at rest, right?
He was still agonizing over that he caused this person's death.
אשקיוהו סמא דשינתא, Ashkyuhu samma de-shinta, they made him drink some type
of a, of a, of a potion that made him fall asleep,
okay, they put him under anesthesia.
ועיילוהו לביתא דשישא, Ve-ayiluhu le-veita de-shisha, they brought him into a house
of marble, meaning like into a lab, into a, you know, an
operating room which was all like very pure, you know, very protected
there from outside, from the air, you know. וקרעו לכרסיה, Ve-kar'u le-karshei,
and they tore open his stomach.
Now they're going to... והוה מפקא מיניה דיקולי דיקולי דתרבא, ve-hava mapki
minei dikulei dikulei de-tarba, no they wanted to test his fat. No,
no, they weren't killing him. They were basically just doing a, what
do they call it, the liposuction. Okay, seriously, that's what it says.
No way. Yeah, yeah, they're going to test whether that's going to
be true about his fat or not, so in order to put
his mind at rest. Okay, so they removed baskets and baskets filled
with fat. Okay, so he was pretty fat. ואותבי בשמשא, Ve-otvei be-shimsha,
and they put it in the sun, בתמוז, be-Tammuz, in Tammuz, which
is a hot, hot summer month, ואב, ve-Av, Tammuz and Av, ולא
מסריח, ve-lo masriach,
and it did not spoil. So you see he was right. Okay,
that look, you know, he... it proved how much more so that
his gut was correct, you know exactly what he said was true,
okay, about his fat. So the גמרא Gemara says what do you
mean? כל תרבא נמי לא סריח, kol tarba nami la sariach, so
normal fat also doesn't spoil. I don't know what it means by
that anyway. כל תרבא לא סריח, kol tarba la sariach,
normal fat doesn't spoil, but שורקי סומקי shurakei sumkei מסריח, masriach, but
ones that has like red veins in it, that does spoil. הכא,
Hacha, אף על גב דאיכא שורקי סומקי, af al gav de-ika shurakei
sumkei, here even the fat his fat that had the red veins
in it, לא מסריח, lo masriach, didn't spoil. So he had another
validation that he had acted correctly. Okay now even if it was
true that he had had acted correctly in the sense that this
guy, you know, it's sort of like what it actually it just
strikes me this actually quite powerful, you know, because it's like, um,
you know when you read about how bad sometimes our legal system
is, right, and how people are pressured to, you know, to...
what do you call it? To... thank you, to confess, and you
know, and how sometimes prosecutors really like will... will pressure witnesses to
say things that aren't
true. You know, but anyway, but that's sort of the thing here.
Well, okay, maybe he wasn't guilty of that, but he was guilty
of something else. But nevertheless, you know, that doesn't exactly clear your
conscience because you're acting in certain ways and that's not why you
did it, and you want to know that, you know, now you
feel in yourself that you can actually,
you know, misuse your power, right? And you act in ways that,
at least in your understanding, what you know, as you understood the
facts of that case, was actually not a just way of acting.
Okay. The whole thing on that ancient practice of opening up the
innards of an animal and checking them, that's interesting. Like, yeah, I
know what you're talking about. Yeah, yeah, yeah, the check, yeah, entrails,
looking at the entrails. Interesting. Maybe. I hear that. That's interesting. Aha.
So קרא אנפשיה Karei anafsheih so he called on himself אף בשרי
ישכון לבטח. af besari yishkon lavetach. Even my flesh will dwell in
confidence, meaning, you know, in security, meaning even when I die, I
know now that the worms won't eat away at it. So he's
מפוייס mefuyas by the way. Yeah, he is, but you know, it
does seem like at the end he's מפוייס, mefuyas, you know, he
puts his mind at rest. But let's keep on reading because the
גמרא Gemara is not the גמרא Gemara is obviously not fully happy.
While the גמרא Gemara is telling the story, it's also not fully
happy about the just being involved in this practice. So let's take
a look. ואף רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, V'af Rabi Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi,
even Rabbi Ishmael the son of Rabbi Yosi, כי מטא כי האי
מעשה לידיה, ki mata ki hai ma'aseh l'yadeih, he found himself in
a similar circumstance as רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Shimon.
He was assigned to be a policeman or, you know, to catch
thieves amongst the Jewish community. פגע ביה אליהו, Paga beih Eliyahu, Elijah
encountered him, אמר ליה, amar leih, top of eighty-four a, said to
him, עד מתי אתה מוסר עמו של אלקינו להריגה, Ad matai atah
moseir amo shel Elokeinu l'harigah, how long will you be handing over
our people to be executed? אמר ליה, Amar leih, מאי אעביד, mai
a'avid, what should I do? הרמנא דמלכא הוא, harmana d'malka hu, it's
the king's orders. אמר ליה, Amar leih, אבוך ערק לאסיא. avuch arak
l'Asya. Okay, if you're only doing it because you're compelled to, so
run away. Better to run away than to than to do something
that might cause innocent death. Your father, maybe they were from a
family, right, that had status and that's why the king sort of
assigned him this task. So your father ran away to אסיא, Asya,
Asia Minor presumably. את ערק ללודקייא, at arak l'Ludkaya, you can run
away to לודקייא, Ludkaya, wherever that is. Okay, so run away. Better
to run away than to do it and to send people to
be executed. So
כי הוי מיקלע רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי... ki havah mikla Rabi Yishmael
b'Rabi Yosi... Okay, so that was sort of the end of the
story about the policeman and the point like there are always alternatives,
okay? And you know, even though the story in the end said
that רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar whatever, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabi Elazar
b'Rabi Shimon did the right thing in the end, it certainly shows
you the tremendous risks that there are about this. So clearly you
can't look at this גמרא Gemara and say ah, you see that
the גמרא Gemara is okay with people being involved in this. It's
clear the גמרא Gemara is not, you know, feels you need to
do what you do to get out of it. Obviously, there's tremendous
risks about catching the wrong person even if you're trying to do
the right thing, about abuse of power and so on. Yes. But
again, did you care to, you know, contextualize this? To the fact
that this is only because there's a great and deep and equal
and harsh disparity between our laws... let's say it was the same
law. Let's say it was like okay, you get in jail and
or you have to pay we pay whatever law. Yeah, but... yeah,
I mean, there's no sense here like if you're given the discretion
to determine who's innocent and who's guilty and so on, right, it
doesn't seem like the law was presumably were were
intrinsically unfair. The punishment might have been disproportionate, but the punishment nowadays
is very disproportionate, right? I mean, you know, there's a few cases
that the הלכה halacha assigns somebody to be put to death and
whatever or to be lashes, but often, you know, the types of
punishments when people are sent to prison is just completely disproportionate to
what the תורה Torah would assign for similar types of things. So
anyway,
but yeah, I mean, this sense of this is because of the
disproportionate punishment. It's not like you shouldn't be involved in trying to
catch bad guys. It's how much you're giving them over to execution.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, now that we're talking
about these two rabbis that were involved in this, so one story
we already know that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Shimon
was very, you know, was very obese or was obese. Here we're
going to say the same thing about רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Rabi
Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi. Okay, so let's take a look. And now it's
going to become a little interesting, the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, כי הוו
מיקלעי רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Ki havu mikla'ei
Rabi Yishmael b'Rabi Yosi v'Rabi Elazar b'Rabi Shimon, when these two would
would encounter one another בהדי הדדי, bahadi hadadi, okay,
so as they would bump into one another, so they were so
overweight that הוי עיילי בקרי דתורי בינייהו ולא הוו נגעי בהו. havah
ayili bikrei d'torei beinaihu v'lo havu nag'ei behu. So
one of my students said this is an exaggeration. You could have
a team of oxen passing under the under their bellies, right, under
the airspace created by, you know, where their bellies would meet, and
the oxen would not touch the two of them. Their bellies would
protrude so much. They'd also have to be very high, I guess,
you know, they'd have to be very tall. Anyway, okay, ולא נגעי
בהו. v'lo nag'ei behu. Okay, אמרה להו ההיא מטרוניתא, Amrah lehu hahi
matronita, so a certain matron, a certain non-Jewish, you know, sort of
woman of status, said to them, בניכם אינם שלכם, Beneichem einam shelachem,
your children are not your own. How are you able to have
intercourse with your wives? You're so fat! So, אמרו לה
*amru lah*, they said to her, שלהן גדול משלנו *shelahen gadol mishelanu*.
No, our wives are bigger than us. Okay, now רש״י Rashi *Rashi*
has two interpretations. One means their bellies are bigger than our bellies,
which doesn't answer the question, right? How are they able to have
intercourse? The other thing they say is that their desire is stronger
than our desire, you know, sexual desire. So she said back that,
so well, so they were saying they make it work somehow, but
here's her response. So קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*, so all the more
so that your children are not yours. So according to the first
explanation, if they're even more overweight than you, it makes it even
harder to have intercourse. And according to the other explanation that they
have more sexual desire, then maybe they're looking to be satisfied elsewhere.
That doesn't answer your question. Is that the מטרוניתא *matrona* speaking גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*-lish? That's true. Although קל וחומר *kal v'chomer* might be the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying this, not the מטרוניתא *matrona*. Okay, either way,
the answer is that's not an answer. So איכא דאמרי *ika d'amri*,
others say, הכי אמרו לה *hachi amru lah*, this is what they
said to her. כי כאיש גבורתו *ki k'ish gvurato*, like a man
is his strength, with רש״י *Rashi*, which means that the sexual desire,
you know, allows us to do what needs to be done. Okay,
איכא דאמרי *ika d'amri*,
and others say, איכא דאמרי *ika d'amri*, where are we, הכי אמרו
לה *hachi amru lah*, אהבה דוחקת את הבשר *ahavah dochekes es habasar*,
the love manages to push, you know, to compress the flesh. So
it doesn't matter, we get it done. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
דלמה להו לאהדורי לה *d'lama lehu l'hadurei lah*, why did they even
bother to respond to her? This is so unseemly.
So, והא כתיב *v'ha ksiv*, doesn't the verse say, אל תען כסיל
כאולתו *al taan k'sil k'ivalto*? Do not respond to a foolish person
according to his foolishness, like it's better to, you know, not engage
than to try to respond, it pulls you down responding. That should
be the basic, like, headline of ninety-eight percent of social media, especially
comments on social media. אל תען כסיל כאולתו *al taan k'sil k'ivalto*,
it just pulls you down, right? Don't get into it, don't have
those discussions. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, שלא להוציא לעז על בניהם
*shelo l'hotzi la'az al beneihem*. No, no, no. Now she was claiming
their children weren't theirs. She wasn't just saying, oh, how do you
have sex with your wives? She was actually making claims of raising
questions about their children, they had to respond. Now, because we had
that answer, כי כאיש גבורתו *ki k'ish gvurato*, and I actually, if
you look at רש״י *Rashi*, right, two lines down in the narrow
lines, רש״י *Rashi* says, אבר תשמיש *ever tashmish*. Okay, which basically means,
right, whatever, you know, that their penis grew in order to their
sexual desire in order to get the job done. So because of
that, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now has the next discussion. Okay, so
let's take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabi Yochanan, *Amar Rabbi
Yochanan*, אבריה דרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי *evrei d'Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose*,
so one of these was רבי Rebbe ישמעאל ברבי יוסי *Rabbi Yishmael
bar Rabbi Yose*, his אבר *ever*, which almost definitely means his penis,
כחמת בת תשעה קבין *k'chamas bat tisha kabin*, was like a water
flask nine קבין *kavin*. I don't know, we're going to read this.
אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said, אבריה
דרבי יוחנן *evrei d'Rabbi Yochanan*, the one of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan,
*Rabbi Yochanan*, כחמת בת חמישה קבין *k'chamas bat chamisha kabin*, was like
a water flask five קבין *kavin*, ואמרי לה בת שלשה קבין *v'amri
lei bat shlosha kabin*, some say three קבין *kavin*. So רב פפא
גופיה *Rav Pappa gufeina*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* himself, because he was
the one saying this about רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, כדיקולי
דהרפני *k'dikurei d'harfini*, was like the, what does רש״י *Rashi* say this
is, oh, like the baskets that they made in הרפני *Harfini*. Oh,
you came at a good time, Jen. Okay, so, so now why
are they talking about this? Well, I mean, obviously they had just
mentioned the question about how they managed to have intercourse given whatever,
so this is, you know, that's obviously where this digressed from, but
nevertheless, it seems to be very inappropriate. So some ראשונים *Rishonim* say,
because it seems so inappropriate, that they're talking actually about their size
and their weight, and not their penis, which is not what the
normal אבר *ever* normally means, but going back to the theme of
being fat. Okay, and for that, תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafot* says, if you
look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, seems to be what תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
understood it, because תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* said, אלו דברים נכתבו *elu dvarim
nichtvu*, אמר רבי Amar Rebbi, יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, אבריה דרבי ישמעאל
*evrei d'Rabbi Yishmael*, אלו דברים נכתבו שלא להוציא לעז על בני אדם
שהם כך *elu dvarim nichtvu shelo l'hotzi la'az al bnei adam shehem
kach*. Okay, to not just sort of, you know, say bad things
about people that are like this. So if it's talking about being
overweight, then you certainly understand it, but I'm not sure. These guys
are overweight then. Yeah, well, that's what we had before, we knew
that they were overweight. That was the whole story, that they were
so fat. I don't know, yeah, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* there's actually
a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in בבא קמא *Bava Kama* that says רב
פפא *Rav Pappa* was very overweight. Okay, so what, though of course,
what תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* might be saying, because of the word לעז
*la'az*, is actually not to say, not to make fun of people
who are fat. תוספות Tosafos? *Tosafot* might be saying people who are
fat, you're going to suspect right that their kids aren't their own
because they're not able to have intercourse with their wives. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is telling you all these fat rabbis, you know,
had the right equipment to have intercourse even though they were fat.
That's probably what תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* is saying. But תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*
has been reframed by, I thought I checked ArtScroll and I checked
Sefaria, as saying, oh, he's talking about that they were too fat,
and so you shouldn't make fun of people who are fat. But
that's not exactly what תוספות *Tosafot* is saying. Okay, the מהרש״א *Maharsha*
says the point is to show you that even though, you know,
even though this was the reality, which presumably reflects a sense or
I don't know, creates a reality or whatever, that it means that
they had a lot of sexual desire, nevertheless they were able to
control their sexual desire and not sin in the sexual realm. But
anyway, it's obviously quite a fascinating גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. Yes. אמר רבי
Rebbi *Amar Rabbi*, are you referring to the second תוספות *Tosafot* where
he says לפי שהשתכר רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan, שהיה מש׳ *l'fi shehistakir
Rabbi Yochanan shehayah mash'* No, we're going to get to that. No,
no. I'm up to the first תוספות. I'm not whether or not
it's really. Okay,
we'll get to that, but we're not up to that. I'm up
to the first תוספות. Okay, אמן. Amen. All right, you're ahead. So
anyway, okay. So all right, so that's the end of that little
story. So now the גמרא Gemara continues like this.
Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan said רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan אנא
משארי דשפירי דירושלים, ana misharei deshifrei de-Yerushalayim, I am the remnant of
some of the the beautiful people that used to live in the
time when there was a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the beautiful people
of Jerusalem. And he's talking about this too because we were talking
about רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan a minute ago in the in that
earlier context and we're talking about like physical appearance and so on,
so it's just a digression. Okay, האי מאן דבעי מחזי שופריה דרבי
יוחנן, Hai man deba'ei mechzi shufrei de-Rabi Yochanan, if you want to
get a sense of the beauty of רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan okay,
נייתי כסא דכספא מבי סלקי, nayeiti kasa de-chaspa mibei salkei, take a
silver goblet that has just come out of the crucible, ונימליה פרצידיא
דרימונא, u-nemalyei partzidei de-rimona,
fill it with pomegranate seeds, סומקא, sumka, red pomegranate seeds,
ונהדר ליה כלילא דוורדא סומקא לפומיה, ve-nahadar lei kelila de-varda sumka le-fumei,
and take like the petals of a rose, of a red rose
and put it around its lip, לפומיה, le-fumei,
maybe that's supposed to show his lips, anyway there's obviously a ruddiness
to his appearance, okay, ונותביה בין שמשא לטולא, ve-notvei bein shimsha le-tula,
and put it in the space between direct sunlight and shade, like
indirect sunlight, ההוא זהרורי מעין שופריה דרבי יוחנן, hahu zaharurei me-ein shufrei
de-Rabi Yochanan, that shining gives you a sense of the glow of
that רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan. would have, okay, the glow of his
skin maybe. Yeah, is this the light that we read about in
the, you know, when the Romans are killing the the sages? Oh,
no, no, that was earlier. That was that but yes, that was
also another beautiful rabbi but that was an earlier no that was
an earlier generation. Yeah things, those, standards of beauty have changed because,
you know, because he was obviously a very portly kind of man.
I mean, back then, since a lot of people were very emaciated,
that's why you know in the paintings from a while back like
people, you know, corpulent people, like you know, shows like, oh you're
healthy. Yeah, I mean, so you're correct, meaning the whole issue about
being so weighty and so corpulent, right, is you know, for us
that's not a sign of beauty, right, which is why clearly that
wasn't what whatever, but but but for from sort of the Persian
society it was. So from like a גמרא written in בבל Bavel
that that's a way of actually speaking about how, you know, beautiful
that they were or how how good-looking and so on. Right, because
here you have רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan consistent with that it seems
that רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan was fat based on the earlier context
in which it was discussed, okay. And here saying about how beautiful
he was. We have to remember this very vivid description when we
get to the סוגיא sugya with ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. We're going
to get to that. Okay, איני, Eini, it's coming at the bottom
of the דף. daf. איני, Eini, is that true? והאמר מר, Ve-ha-amar
mar,
is that true that רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan was so, you know,
beautiful and so on and תוספות you know says since we said
before about that he was a little bit out of the ordinary
in other ways he's out of the ordinary in this way that
was the תוספות that דוב Dov was referring to. Is that true
that he was so amazingly beautiful? והאמר מר, Ve-ha-amar mar, the master
teaches, שופריה דרב כהנא, shufrei de-Rav Kahana, the beauty of רב כהנא,
Rav Kahana, מעין שופריה דרבי אבהו, me-ein shufrei de-Rabi Abbahu, is a
little bit of the beauty of רבי אבהו, Rabi Abbahu, שופריה דרבי
אבהו, shufrei de-Rabi Abbahu, and the beauty of רבי אבהו, Rabi Abbahu,
מעין שופריה דיעקב אבינו, me-ein shufrei de-Yaakov Avinu, is a bit of
the you know gives you a glimmer of the beauty of יעקב,
Yaakov, as a it's a drop of the beauty of יעקב, Yaakov,
and שופריה דיעקב אבינו, shufrei de-Yaakov Avinu, and the beauty of יעקב
אבינו, Yaakov Avinu, מעין שופריה דאדם הראשון, me-ein shufrei de-Adam HaRishon, is
a drop of the beauty of the of the you know first
man, is an is a sense of the beauty of the first
human created. ואילו רבי יוחנן לא קחשיב ליה, Ve-ilu Rabi Yochanan lo
kachashiv lei, so here you have clearly talking about who were all
the you know beautiful men in the you know on our history
and it didn't mention רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan So how could רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan have been so beautiful if he wasn't in this
list? So the גמרא says, no, שאני רבי יוחנן דהדרת פנים לא
הויא ליה. shani Rabi Yochanan de-hadrat panim lo havya lei.
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan was different because he did not have the
glory of the face. What does the glory of the face mean?
So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, הדרת פנים,
hadrat panim, רש"י Rashi says,
זקן, zakan, a beard, okay. So for all the people who don't
have beards like myself or whatever, oh, so you know, oh, you
know, where's your הדרת פנים? hadrat panim? That's like a ישיביש Yeshivish
type of thing people say, you know. I'm serious, like you know,
if you don't have a beard you don't have a הדרת פנים
hadrat panim yet, you know, so they say it's like a young
guy, you know, oh don't worry you'll get older you'll get a
beard you'll have a הדרת פנים. hadrat panim. Anyway, it's a nice
פרום frum way of about, that's what it means to look good
from a פרום frum perspective is to have a beard. Now the
funny thing is and why did רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan not have
a beard? It wasn't like men certainly Jewish men shaved back in
רש"י Rashi says הדרת פנים hadrat panim זקן. zakan. I don't know
where is he? He says הדרת פנים hadrat panim זקן. zakan. It's
one word the רש"י. Rashi. End of. Anyway, so why why did
he not have a beard, right? I mean did he not grow
facial hair? I mean some men don't grow facial hair well. Anyway
תוספות says it probably it doesn't really necessarily mean that. תוספות says
where's תוספות? Oh maybe it wasn't תוספות, maybe oh no it was
the מהרש"א. Maharsha. I think the מהרש"א Maharsha just says no, it
just means that he might have had this amazing glow which is
what we're talking about, like this like aura around him, but it
doesn't necessarily mean that he was handsome in terms of his facial
features, you know, his facial features. were in such that made him,
you know, even with, because before we were really talking about like
the glow almost of his skin or you know, type of an
aura, but it doesn't still not the same as these. Okay. רבי
יוחנן הוה אזיל ויתיב אשערי טבילה. Rebbe Yochanan hava azil veyasiv asha’arei
tvilah. Now we mentioned how beautiful רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan was. It
is interesting also that it's using, you know, terms of beauty, not
of being handsome. I don't know actually, it's a good question. Why?
I mean you have it in this week in the פרשה, Parsha,
right? יוסף
היה יפה תואר ויפה מראה. Yosef hayah yefeh to'ar veyefeh mareh. It
uses the same words it uses for beautiful women, right? Did they
have a different word just used to describe handsomeness as opposed to
beauty? I don't know. So anyway, here רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan would
go ויתיב אשערי טבילה veyasiv asha’arei tvilah and would sit by the
gates where the women would go down to go to the מקוה.
mikvah. Okay, whether it's a מקוה mikvah or body of water. Okay.
And that then when they would be leaving that area they would
see him. אמר כי סלקן בנות ישראל מטבילת מצוה, Amar ki salkan
bnot Yisrael mitvilat mitzvah, when the Jewish women, the daughters of Israel,
come up from the immersion of מצוה, mitzvah, going to the, you
know, to immerse themselves so that they can be with their husbands,
לפגעו בי, lifge’u bi, let them encounter me first thing כי היכי
דלהוו להו בני שפירי כוותי ki heichi delahavei lehu bnei shapiri kavasi
that they should have children as beautiful as me because they'll see
me and that'll make an impression on them. And this gets to
sort of like we just read last week or whatever it was,
last week, two weeks ago in the פרשה, Parsha, you know, יעקב
Yaakov sort of striped and doing the stripes and the sticks and
the sheep see them when they mate and it leads to having,
you know, striped and speckled sheep or whatever. This belief that things
that somebody is thinking about at the moment of conception affects how
the child will actually turn out and what the child will look
like. So he wants these women to be thinking of him. Right.
So that is of course a difficult issue, which is is that,
is that the גמרא in נדרים Nedarim makes it clear that, you
know, you're not supposed to be thinking of somebody other than their
spouse while you're having sex. So how come he is not bothered
with this? So it raises interesting questions about, now one way to
say this is he doesn't mean at the moment that they're having
sex, he means that if it's the first thing they encounter
afterwards, that just by itself creates that impact because תוספות quotes another
גמרא that speaks about, you know, about a woman being careful who
or what she encounters right after she comes up from the מקוה.
mikvah. So it might not be that what they're thinking during sex.
Or it might be that the issue about what you're thinking about
during, the questions about what a person's allowed to think about or
who a person's allowed to think about during sex are not sort
of exactly as black and white as maybe some other גמרות Gemaros
would indicate. But that's like a different discussion which I'm not going
to have right now. Okay, so the גמרא says like this.
What? Right, listen to a podcast, upcoming podcast or previous one, I
don't remember. Anyway, so the גמרא says like this. Okay. כי היכי
דלהוו לי בני שפירי כוותי ki heichi delahavei li bnei shapiri kavasi
וגמירי אורייתא כוותי vegmiri oraisa kavasi
and they should be as learned in תורה Torah as me, which
is interesting, right, because even that's not an image that anybody would
see, right? It's just so, but somehow because that is who רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan was, that somehow would impact the child as well.
אמרו ליה רבנן, Amru leh rabanan, so the rabbis said to him,
לא מסתפי מר מעינא בישא, lo mistafi mar me'ina bisha, are you
not worried about the עין הרע? ayin hara? They didn't say to
him, are you not worried about them having improper sexual thoughts, you
having improper sexual thoughts? That they didn't ask. They said, are you
not worried about the עין הרע, ayin hara, meaning you're putting yourself
on display that people should see you're so beautiful, so you're just
asking for, you know, something to happen to your beauty, right? That's,
you know, that's the עין הרע ayin hara idea. אמר להו, amar
lehu, he said to them,
אנא מזרעא דיוסף קאתינא, ana mizar'a diYosef kasina, I am descendant of
יוסף Yosef דלא שלטא ביה עינא בישא, delo shalta bei eina bisha,
he's protected from the עין הרע. ayin hara. דכתיב בן פורת יוסף,
deksiv ben porat Yosef, a child of like of a,
you know, what's the word פורת, porat, right, multiple, right, to a
fecundity or something. Anyway, as יוסף, Yosef, בן פורת עלי עין, ben
porat alei ayin, a child of, of you know, a fecundity, we'll
use that word, over the eye, so or עלי עין alei ayin
could also mean over a wellspring. So that means that it rises
above the evil eye. ואמר רבי אבהו, Ve'amar Rebbe Abahu, אל תקרי
עלי עין אלא עולי עין, al tikrei alei ayin ela olei ayin,
to rise above the evil eye. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא אמר מהכא
Rebbe Yose bar Rebbe Chanina amar mehacha מהפסוק הבא mehapassuk haba וידגו
לרוב בקרב הארץ, Veyidgu larov bekerev ha'aretz, they shall multiply like fish,
that's the word ידגו yidgu in the midst of the land. מה
דגים שבים מים מכסים אותם, Mah dagim shebayam mayim michasim osam, the
same way fish, fish in the sea the water covers them ואין
העין שולטת בהן ve'ein ha'ayin sheletes bahen and the eye can't see
them so that they can multiply hidden from the eye, from the
seeing eye, אף זרעו של יוסף, af zar'o shel Yosef, so the
seed of יוסף, Yosef, because that's talking about אפרים Ephraim ומנשה, uMenashe,
אין העין שולטת בהן, ein ha'ayin sheletes bahen,
the eye won't have control over them. Fine. יומא
חד, Yoma chad, since we were talking about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and how beautiful he was and the women and water, we get
to the next story about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, and his beauty
and water and this is the famous רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rebbe
Yochanan veReish Lakish story. יומא חד, Yoma chad, one day הוי קא
סחי רבי יוחנן בירדנא, hava ka sachi Rebbe Yochanan beYardenah, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan was bathing himself in the Jordan River. חזייה ריש לקיש,
Chazayei Reish Lakish, presumably naked, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish saw him ושוור
לירדנא אבתריה, veshavar leYardenah avasrei, he jumped into the Jordan to go
after him. אמר ליה, Amar leh, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. said
to him, it's not exactly clear, does רש״י say? No. What? Thought
he was a woman, thought he had long hair, thought he was...
Maybe they say
he thought he was a woman? He had no beard. Oh, he
had no beard, if you want to be consistent with that. Okay,
maybe. Right, well,
he certainly was beautiful. Right, so that's interesting. Okay, I mean, so
yeah. Okay, so it's a good point. So maybe he thought he
was a woman and he was going to try and to, you
know, seize her, have sex with her or whatever. אבתריה. Abatrei. אמר
ליה, Amar Lei, so Rabbi Yochanan said to him—well that certainly is
consistent with the continuation of the story—חילך לאורייתא, Cheilech Le'Oraisa, your
your strength should be devoted to learning Torah. Okay, you know, here
you are, you are able to jump in from wherever he was,
maybe from a cliff, to swim to the middle of the Jordan
to chase after me because you thought I was a woman. We'll
go with that explanation. Okay, that type of strength should be devoted
to learning Torah. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, he said back to him,
שופרך לנשי, Shufrach Lenashei, your beauty belongs to women. Okay, so, you
know, my strength belongs to Torah. You you you know your beauty,
so women should have your beauty. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so what
he responds to that? So Rabbi Yochanan said back, אי הדרת בך,
Ei Hadart Bach, if you do teshuvah, יהבינא לך אחתא דשפירא מינאי,
Yahivna Lach Achtah Deshapira Minai,
I'll give you my sister to marry, she's more beautiful than I
am. Nobody's asking the sister this, but okay. קביל עליה. Kabil Alei.
Now,
the fact that he says do teshuvah shows that, you know, he
there was something about him that needed to do teshuvah for. From
this story, maybe the most immediate is that he was running after
women, jumping after naked women what he believed to be naked women
in the Jordan. But anyway, we'll see as the story continues. Okay,
קביל
עליה, Kabil Alei, he accepted upon him to do teshuvah and ultimately
to learn Torah. Okay, because he said חילך לאורייתא, Cheilech Le'Oraisa, so
he's pushing him to learn Torah. Okay, בעי למהדר לאתויי מניה, Ba'ei
Lemehadar Le'atuyei Manei, he wanted to go back to the edge of
the Jordan to retrieve his belongings. ולא מצי הדר, Velo Matzi Hadar,
and he he lost his strength. He wasn't able to. Okay, because,
you know, as Rashi says, you know, accepting upon himself the yoke
of Torah sapped some of his strength from him. Of course, which
is so funny. He said your strength should go to learning Torah,
so now that it went to learning Torah he doesn't have it
for physical purposes. Like it was a sublimation, right? In other words,
all of his strength, as it were, not sexually was sapped, but
because of learning Torah. Right, right, but then now he doesn't have
it for physical exertion. Right. So okay, ולא
מצי הדר. Velo Matzi Hadar. אקריה Akrei Rabbi Yochanan taught him מקרא
Mikra ואתניה Ve'atnei taught him משנה. Mishnah. ושויא גברא רבא, Veshavyei Gavra
Rabba, he turned him into a a big person, meaning a big
talmid chacham. יומא חד הוו מפלגי בי מדרשא, Yoma Chad Hevu Miflagi
Bei Midrasha, one day the Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish were arguing
in the beis medrash. And here was the Mishnah. It was a
Mishnah in Kelim. הסייף
והסכין
והפגיון והרומח ומגל יד, Hassayif Vehasakin Ve'hapigyon Veharomach Umagal Yad, the sword
and the dagger and the pigyon, I don't know what it is,
a knife, the spear, the dagger, the spear and a scythe, a
hand-scythe, ומגל קציר, Umagal Katzir, and a scythe used for like harvesting.
מאימתי מקבלין טומאה, Me'eimatai Mekablin Tuma, when do they when are they
considered to be finished vessels and can become tamei? משעת גמר מלאכתן,
Mishe'as Gmar Melachtan, when they're finished with the, you know, when they're
finished. ומאימתי גמר מלאכתן, Ume'eimatai Gmar Melachtan, and when are they done
being constructed? What's the stage? רבי יוחנן אומר משציחצחן בכבשן, Rabbi Yochanan
Omer Mishetzitchtzechun Bekivshan, Rabbi Yochanan says, so this was that was the
Mishnah, now the Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish are debating what what
you know when that is. So Rabbi Yochanan says from the time
they're done being smelted in the in the in the furnace, in
the right. וריש לקיש אמר משציחצחן במים, Vereish Lakish Amar Mishetzitchtzechun Bamayim,
no, no, that's not done, you have to then sort of, you
know, polish them and rub them with water, that finishes and hardens
the metal. So אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so Rabbi Yochanan said, אה
ליסטא בלסטיותיה ידע, Ah Lista Belistyutei Yada, oh, you know, the the
bandit knows his banditry. Oh, of course you know this, you know,
because you're you're that's that's your field. That was not a nice
thing to say. Right, it was not at all nicely to say.
What happened to the Gemara earlier that spoke about אונאת דברים, Ona'as
Devarim, or hurting people about their past? Or whatever, nobody says it
was the right thing for Reb to do. You know, he may
be just like, you know, sometimes you say stupid things, you know,
it slips out or whatever. Okay, and it wasn't even clear, was
he angry at him, that you know was he just saying, "Oh,
of course you know this! Yeah, that's your field," right? So anyway,
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so what?
So wait, the Gemara's going to continue, the story isn't over. Okay,
now by the way, I should say that this thing about being
a bandit, okay, there's no other there isn't other evidence about this,
that he was a bandit. And Rashi says, you know, "Okay, he
was a bandit," whatever. We're going to continue in the Gemara, it's
going to Rashi's going to read it through that lens, but Tosafos
actually says that from the fact that Rabbi Yochanan said to him
do teshuvah and as well I'll tell you in a minute how
Tosafos reads the continuation of the Gemara, shows that Reish Lakish originally
was a talmid chacham and he had just gone off the path
for a while and then Rabbi Yochanan was saying to him do
teshuvah. Okay, it doesn't sound like that because it says he had
to teach him Mikra and Mishnah. But anyway, so but Tosafos anyway
tries to read that in, although that's a hard read. But nevertheless,
it's not, you know, this idea that we have that he was
a bandit is not so well-based in sources. It's like basically based
on the one reference in this story. Okay, so let's take a
look. And in the footnote in Birnbaum. Yeah, so okay. ליסטא בלסטיותיה
ידע. Lista Belistyutei Yada.
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, ומאי אהנית לי, Umai Ahant Li, what good
did this do me that I
did teshuvah? התם רבי קרו לי. Hasam Rabbi Karu Li. master there
and I'm a different master here. Okay, again, תוספות *Tosafot* says no,
I used to be a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* and then I
left and then I came back or whatever. Anyway, okay, but within
this context it seems like the way רש״י *Rashi* reads it certainly
that this is not meant as a just a סתם *stam* remark.
He really had been a bandit and then he said, okay, so
if you're going to call me those names or whatever, what good
is all this that I did? And why was I coming to
learn תורה Torah, *Torah*? So that you could pull... you could say
those things about me. So, okay. אמר ליה אהני לך *Amar lei
hanei lach*, what are you talking about what good did I do
for you? I benefited you not that you should get some type
of honor, but I benefited you דקריבתך תחת כנפי השכינה *d'karivtach tachas
kanfei shechina*, that I brought you under the wings of the divine
protection, right? I brought you to תורה Torah, *Torah*. That itself is
a benefit, not the honor that you get from
it. Okay. So חלש דעתיה דרבי יוחנן *chala daiteih d'Rabbi Yochanan*. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* felt very, was very hurt, was
very pained by this, that it sounded like ריש לקיש Resh Lakish,
*Reish Lakish* was not grateful that he had brought him closer to
תורה *Torah*.
And because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* felt that way, the
result was חלש ריש לקיש Resh Lakish? *chala Reish Lakish*. So חלש
דעתיה דרבי יוחנן *chala daiteih d'Rabbi Yochanan*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi
Yochanan* felt bad and that led to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* actually
becoming sick. It was even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan* that
caused it.
I understand. It was all coming from רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi
Yochanan*, right, and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* was just, when ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish* was responding what good does this do for me, he
presumably did not really mean it, he was just responding about being
insulted. Okay, anyway, so let's take a look. So ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish* got sick. אתאי אחתיה *asai achaseih*, so now רבי Rebbe יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*’s sister, who we’ll remember at this stage in the story
is ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*’s wife, okay, although we didn’t actually say
that explicitly, that that happened. וקבכיין *v'kabachyan*, she was crying to him.
אמר ליה *Amar lei* and said to him, עשה בשביל בני *asai
bishvil beni*, pray that he should get better for the sake of
my son. I don’t want my son to be without a father.
Her brother, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. אמר לה amar lah *Amar la*,
he said to her, עזבה יתומיך אני אחיה *azva yasomayich ani achayeh*.
Abandon your orphans, I will support them. All right, so your orphans
don’t worry I’ll take care of them. Which is like he’s okay
that ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* is going to die. He must have
felt so offended. עשה בשביל אלמנותי *asai bishvil almanusi*, but do for
the sake of my widowhood, don’t let me become a widow. אמר
לה *Amar la*, he said to her at the end of that
פסוק *pasuk* from ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu*, ואלמנותיך עלי תבטחו *vealmanotayich alai tivtachu*. Your
widowhood, I will take care of... have trust in me. Don’t worry,
I’ll take care of you as a widow. So he really didn’t
care. He was so upset. Okay, it's interesting, right before remember the
rabbi got upset and seized the guy as a גנב *ganev* and
he got killed or whatever. So there's certain echoes of this. רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* got upset. This guy was about being a גנב
*ganev* who no longer was a גנב *ganev* and now the guy
died as a result. Okay. And before we had regret and now
we’re going to have regret. So there’s an interesting parallel here. והוה
קמיצטער רבי
יוחנן
בתריה טובא *v'hava kamitztayer Rabbi Yochanan basrei tuva*, and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* was anguished after,
enormously anguished after his death. אמרו רבנן amru rabanan *Amru Rabbanan*, so
the rabbis said, מאן ליזיל ליתיב לדעתיה *man lizei liyaseiv lidaiteih*? Who
will go and sort of settle his mind? Console him in some
way. He doesn't have his prized תלמיד *talmid*, almost his like as
we know he was sort of like a תלמיד חבר *talmid chaver*,
like a תלמיד *talmid* who was also even a colleague. So who’s
going to go and help us do something about that? So ניזיל
רבי אלעזר Elazar. בן פדת *neizil Rabbi Elazar ben Pedat*. Let’s send
רבי אלעזר Elazar. בן פדת *Rabbi Elazar ben Pedat*. דמחדד שמעתיה *d'mechadid
shmaiteih*. He is very sharp. So he’ll be a good sparring partner
with רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. אזל יתיב קמיה *azal yasiv kameih*. He
went and sat in front of him. כל מילתא דהוה אמר רבי
יוחנן *kol milsa d'hava amar Rabbi Yochanan*, anytime רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
would say something, אמר ליה תניא Tanya, דמסייעא לך *amar lei tanya
d'mesaye'a lach*. Oh, I’ve got a great ברייתא *brayta* that supports what
you’re saying. I’ve got this source that supports what you’re saying, that
source that supports what you’re saying. אמר את כבר לקישא *Amar at
ke-Bar Lakisha*? Are you supposed to be like ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*?
בר לקישא *Bar Lakisha*, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, right, בר לקיש *ben
Lakish*. בר לקישא *Bar Lakisha*, whenever I would say something, he didn't
support me. הוה מקשי לי עשרין וארבע קושייתא *hava makshi li esrin
v'arba kushi'ata*. He would ask 24 questions. He’d challenge me from every
type of direction. ומפרקנא *umfarikna*, then I would have to respond and
answer, והוה עשרין וארבע פירוקי *v'hava esrin v'arba perukei*, 24 answers. וממילא
רווחא שמעתיה *umimeila ravcha shmaiteih*. And through that, the learning became
better, clearer. רווחא *ravcha* actually means like wider, expanded. Right, thank you,
expanded. Right, the corpus of knowledge expanded. I said... it's still in
a funny metaphor, expanding, because you would have said like had been
more precise and sharper and more exact. To ask questions, you have
to nuance things in a better way, right? But anyway, the result
still is the body of knowledge expands because we understand things in
a better way, right? הגדיל תורה *higdil Torah*. Exactly. So obviously the
whole point is to be challenged, to force... that gets us all
smarter. ואת אמרת תניא דמסייעא לך *v'at amrat tanya d'mesaye'a lach*? And
you're telling me oh I can support you? Like I don't want
an echo chamber. אטו לא ידענא lo yadana, דשפיר קאמינא *atu lo
yadana d'shapir kamina*? What, you don't think I know that I said
something that makes sense? Of course I know
there's things that
make sense. The Maharsha says a nice thing. Maharsha says after this
he realized that he had not just lost a student but he
had lost a teacher. And once he realized that he writes us
through this being challenged he learned. And since he realized he had
lost a teacher, you do קריעה when a רבי dies. So that's
why he rent his garments. ואמר היכא בר לקיש היכא בר לקיש,
Va'amar eicha Bar Lakish eicha Bar Lakish, where are you ריש לקיש,
where are you ריש לקיש? והוה קאזיל וקא בכי Vahavah kazil veka
bachi and he cried עד דשף דעתיה מיניה ad deshaf da'ateih mineih
until he went out of his mind, until his mind became unsettled,
unseated. He went crazy? Well it doesn't sound like we don't know,
right? It sounds like he lost his senses. So בעו רבנן רחמי
עליה ba'u Rabbanan rachamei aleih
so the רבנן Rabbanan prayed for him, how should he basically live
that way without being in his right mind? ונח נפשיה. venach nafsheih.
So the way that it was his better resolution rather than he
should live not in his right mind was that he should pass
away. So again it's quite fascinating right? I mean this is even
a worse resolution than the other story. The other story, in the
end he was a רשע rasha and in the end whatever you
know you did the surgery but found out that to some degree
it wasn't a terrible thing that happened. Here it was a terrible
thing that happened and both of them wound up dying. ואפילו הכי
Va'afilu hachi
and now as in a radical re-shift of getting back, if you
just were wondering if the parallel wasn't intentional, we're now going to
go back to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon and
his wrong decision that led to the guy being executed. Wait let
me just read this one line for the juxtaposition. ואפילו הכי לא
סמך רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אדעתיה Va'afilu hachi lo samach Rabbi Elazar
beRabbi Shimon ada'ateih
and even though all this thing had happened and it turned out
they said the guy was a רשע, rasha, we're going jumping all
the way back to that, the guy was a רשע, rasha, his
fat didn't stench even left out in the sun, he no longer
trusted himself in terms of his decision-making. Okay, so it's sort of
totally enveloping the רבי יוחנן story and we're now going to be
moving back to the רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon
story. Yes, and
who was earlier? Well רבי יוחנן, רבי יוחנן was an אמורא Amora
but he was like a first generation. I think רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon was also first generation אמורא Amora because
we're going to have רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi sort of,
no, but that would have made him earlier. No, so רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon would have been earlier, would have
been I'm sure Zvi is here he could tell us, but I'm
pretty sure he was a תנא. Tanna. I'm pretty sure he was
a little earlier than רבי יוחנן. Yeah, so this story sorts of
reflects on the power of words that obviously has to do... Yeah,
well right I mean
רבי יוחנן had made that statement. Exactly, this would have been a
perfect story in the אונאת דברים ona'at devarim סוגיא sugya of the
גמרא, right? It's exactly the אונאת דברים. ona'at devarim. You're reminding somebody
about their past and then whatever and then the way they exchange
like offensive you know words that hurt each other's feelings. Right, exactly.
Yeah. So so powerful, these people invested with power. Right, you know,
it's why writing an email, you're really enraged, you
write back a response email, put it in a Word document and
don't press the send button, let it exactly, that's an excellent application,
right? I mean there's so many things about these גמרות, Gemaras, right?
But like you know how do we respond so quickly in emails
and whatever and the impact, that's a good point. Okay, ואפילו הכי
לא סמך רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אדעתיה Va'afilu hachi lo samach Rabbi
Elazar beRabbi Shimon ada'ateih and he still felt look I've done this
terrible thing, I had executed this person without sufficient evidence and he
didn't even with all these signs that he did the right thing
he was not satisfied. קיבל עליה יסורין, Kibel aleih yissurin, he accepted
upon himself afflictions. And we'll sort of see like what does that
mean? He welcomed afflictions we'll see in a minute so באורתא be'orta
apparently he had boils and blisters that covered his body and we'll
see in a minute he like welcomed them on his body and
God I guess agreed to it. ובאורתא Ube'orta and the night הוו
מייתי ליה שיתין נמטי, havu maytei leih shittin namtei, they would lay
sixty cloth sheets underneath him. You know how there's numbers, 40, 24,
or 60, whatever probably exaggeration. נמטי אהנמטי. Namtei ahanamtei. לצפרא Letzafra in
the morning מנגדי מתותיה שיתין משחלי דמא וכיבא. mengadei mituteih shittin mashchalei
dama vechiva. They would remove from underneath him 60 buckets or whatever
vessels of water and blood and pus that had come out of
these sores.
So he was obviously tremendously afflicted in his body afterwards, something he
accepted upon himself as a result of what he had done. ולמחר
עבדא ליה דביתהו שיתין מיני לפדא. Velamachar avda leih deveiteihu shittin minei
lapda. In the morning his wife made him 60 different types of
לפדא lapda which רש"י Rashi says was some type of a fig
dish which was supposed to be for his health. ואכל להו Ve'achal
lehu and he ate it וברי uvari and that gave him strength.
ולא הוי שבקה ליה דביתהו למיפק לבי מדרשא. Velo havay shavka leih
deveiteihu lemipak levei midrasha. His wife wouldn't let him go to the
בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash כי היכי דלא לידחקוהו רבנן ki heichi delo
lidchaku'hu Rabbanan so the רבנן Rabbanan should not put cause him discomfort,
maybe that's just rubbing just if you're with a lot of people
they rub up against your body
or just his mind
you know.
Right, asking so many questions. It's unsettling, he's in physical distress. Yeah,
I don't know. I mean, but you are right, we are going
to see later that he's going to say that the rabbis were
not happy with him because of his what he had done about
catching the גנבים. ganavim. Okay, so maybe you're right, maybe it means
that they shouldn't anguish him with their words or whatever, but we'll
see as the story continues. באורתא אמר להו B'orta amar lehu at
night he would say to them to his sores, his blisters, אחי
ורעי Achai v're'ai my brothers and my friends, באו Bo come, that
he was welcoming these afflictions on his body. ובצפרא אמר להו U'v'tzaphra
amar lehu in the morning he would say to them, זילו מקמי
ביטול תורה Zilu mikamei bittul Torah leave because of your taking me
away from learning Torah. So the sores would like explode you know
on his body at night, he would welcome them but they'd go
away in the morning and he would be able to learn Torah.
יומא חד שמעה דביתהו Yoma chad shamah d'veiteihu one night his wife
heard him saying you know welcoming his sores and his blisters. אמרה
ליה Amrah leih she said to him, עד כבשת להו עילוייך Ad
kabshat lehu illuyaich you are bringing them upon yourself? כלית ממון של
בית אבא Kilis mamon shel beis Abba you have you're destroying all
of my father's wealth, like apparently she was the one with the
money in the family and all of your medical treatments, I mean
60 sheets a night, you know, you know, they're destroying all of
that wealth and you know and you're welcoming this upon yourself?
אימרדא Imrada so she rebelled against him, she left him, אזלה לבית
נשא Azlah l'veis nasha she went to... now בית נשא beis nasha
means like the woman's house or something, it means whatever, different meanings
of the word, but we read it to mean woman's house. Basically,
it's she went to her father's house, but it's also what it's
called when her father's no longer alive. So what do you call
the house of the patriarch when the patriarch is no longer alive?
So you call it the woman's house, because only like the women
are left behind. Okay, but anyway she went to her mother's house,
so she went back to her to you know to her father's
house. סליקו ואתו הנהו נחשיסין ספונאי Seliku v'asu hanahu nachshisin saphunai so
now who's going to take care of Rabbi Elazar ben Rabbi Shimon?
So 60
sailors came up from the ocean and אייתו ליה שיתין עבדי ayisu
leih shittin avdei and they presented him with 60 slaves to take
care of him. כי הנהו שיתין גיבורים ki hanahu shittin gibborim like
it's maybe? Oh, that's interesting. דנקיטי שיתין ארנקי D'nakiti shittin arnaki and
they were holding on to 60 wallets. Okay, they basically brought him
60 slaves, each slave I don't know if each slave had 60
wallets, okay, it's sort of like when I was going to St.
Ives, right? Yeah, anyway, anyway, they had a total of 60 wallets,
each one but purses of silver and of gold and they gave
him all this wealth. ועבדו ליה שיתין מיני לפדא Va'avdu leih shittin
minei lapda they made for him
same like his wife 60 types of this fig dish. ואכל להו
v'achal lehu and he would eat it. So they came to replace
his wife. Tosafos, if you look at Tosafos, Rashi says the same
thing, but Tosafos just says, מפרש במדרש שעמד עליהם נחש בים לטבעם
mifaresh b'midrash she'amad aleihem nachash bayam l'tavam ונדרו לו ושקטה הרוח u'nadru
lo v'shaketah haruach like a Yonah story, right? They were going to
get swamped and they by a sea, you know, by some type
of a storm and they realized and they they took an oath
to like you know give this wealth to a great rabbi, Rabbi
Elazar ben Rabbi Shimon, according to Rashi actually seems like they knew
they prayed on behalf of Rabbi Elazar, like Rabbi Elazar ben Rabbi
Shimon's merit should save us. Whatever reason it was and then they
came and they gave him this wealth. Okay, so יומא חד Yoma
chad one day אמרה לה לברתה amrah lah l'vartah the wife said
to her daughter, his daughter too, זילו בדקי באבוך Zilu bidki b'avuch
go check in on your
father, מאי קא עביד האידנא mai ka avid ha'idna how's he handling
himself these days? אתיא Asyah she came, אמר לה so the father
Rabbi Elazar ben Rabbi Shimon said to her, זיל אימי לאימך Zil
imi l'imeich go back say back to your mother, שלנו גדול משלהם
shelanu gadol mishelahem our wealth now is greater than theirs, which I
presumably means like your family's wealth. You know you were telling me
I was wasting away the wealth of your family, whatever, look, you
know, I'm doing just fine now. קרי אנפשיה Karei anafsheih he said
about himself, היתה כאוניות סוחר ממרחק תביא לחמה Haysa k'oniyos socheir mimmerchak
tavi lachmah which is of course you know he's a little bit
getting back at his wife, right? Because this is said about the
אשת חיל Eishes Chayil and here he's basically saying, no, no, I,
my Torah, you know, because also אשת חיל Eishes Chayil sometimes used
as a metaphor for Torah, was able to bring the stuff, you
know, through the boats from far away, these sailors came and brought
me all this wealth from far
away. אכל ושתי
וברי Achal u'shasi u'vari he ate and drank and he got better.
Now presumably that means that he got that the זקפות zakfos means
like in the normal morning he got better, he got fully better,
but he had been wanting himself to have these sores. Anyway, נפק
לבי מדרשא Nafak l'vei midrasha he went out, whatever it was, at
least in the morning he was feeling good, he generally felt good
in the mornings and now he went to the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash because now his wife wasn't there to prevent him. Exactly. אייתו
לקמיה שיתין מיני דמא Aisu l'kameih shittin minei dama so they brought
him 60 different like visions of blood, meaning
מראות maros you know, like נדה niddah things on cloths.
That's a good way of saying it. He really knows what blood
on cloth looks like. טהרינהו Taharihu and he said they're all טהור.
tahor. Every single one of these women is not a נדה. niddah.
Okay. הוו קמרנני רבנן. Havi kamranini rabanan. So the rabbis were like,
you know, gossiping about him and saying, אמרי סלקא דעתך לית בהו
חד ספק? Amri salkadaitach lavu chad safeik? What? Of sixty people, sixty
different מראות, maros, is there not one that maybe is a problem?
They're all totally טהור? tahor? אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to
them, אם כמותי הוא, im kamosi hu, if it is, if I'm
correct, יחיו יהיו כולם זכרים. yichyu yiyu kulam zecharim.
They should all become pregnant because after that they'll now go to
the מקוה, mikvah, go be with their husbands, maybe echoing that whole
רבי יוחנן story, right? They'll all conceive, have children, and all the
children that should emerge that should come nine months from now will
all be male. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, right,
there's this whole obviously anti-women thing going on here, ואם לאו, ve'im
lav, תהא נקבה אחת ביניהם. tehei nekeiva achas beinehem. If I am
incorrect and they weren't all—I didn't פסקן pasken correctly—then even if there's
one girl amongst them, that'll prove that I'm incorrect. So the likelihood
of having—I want somebody to do the math—if I'm incorrect, they said
incorrect, if I'm wrong. Okay. The likelihood of all being by chance
male is like two to the sixtieth, that's like pretty... okay. היו
כולם זכרים. Hayu kula zecharim. Oh! So they were all male. Shows
that he was
correct. Okay. ואסקו כולהו אלעזר אשמיה. Ve'asku kulhu Elazar ashmay. They
all of the boys were called אלעזר. Okay, so here he was,
as one has to imagine, he's not having sex with his wife,
he's separated with his wife, and now all of these kids are
now conceived and they're all being named אלעזר. Okay, which is also
similar like רבי יוחנן. They saw רבי יוחנן, he was as beautiful
as רבי יוחנן. There's very... a lot of stuff going on here.
תניא, we taught in the בריתא. Baraita. אמר רבי, כמה פריה ורביה
ביטלה רשיעה זו מישראל. kama pirya verivya bitla risha zo miyisrael.
Now this is a very harsh statement. It could mean his wife.
I think by context it sounds like it does. How much, right,
of, you know,
what do you call it? Fertility,
right, that's a better word than פריה ורביה. pirya verivya. What is
it? Procreation, right. How much procreation, right, did this wicked woman prevent
happening from Israel? She, presumably meaning the wife, kept him from the
בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. And therefore look what he was able to
do in one day. All those days he wasn't going to the
בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, he could have פסקן paskened about the blood,
and he could have helped women be together with their husbands. So
that's probably פשט. pshat. רש"י, Rashi, who, you know, wants to tone
it down or whatever, says maybe רשיעה risha means the evil government
that made him into the policeman to begin with that brought all
of this about. Maybe. Okay. Anyway, moving on. Oh, by the way,
it does sound like I mentioned before the question about, about crucifying.
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon and now we're dealing
with רבי or whatever, it seems like all of this just shows
that I get, I don't always get straight exactly, you know, the
geography and the chronology. But it seems like we're dealing with the
תנאים tannaim in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so if Ephraim was here
he could check that, but anyway. So and it is true that
the גמרא does sometimes call Rome, you know, מלכות רשיעה, malchus risha,
the evil government. Okay,
and that would actually mean that he would, you know, that when
it said that they strung somebody else up probably would have meant
that they crucified him. Yes, the Romans crucified, the Persians impaled. Right.
So yeah, we probably are talking about that. Okay. So anyway, כי
הוה קניח נפשיה, ki hava kaniach nafshei,
so now when he was dying, אמר להו לדביתהו, amar lehu lidvasaihu,
he said to his wife. They presumably had reconciled or whatever. He's
still going to speak to his wife before he dies. ידענא ברבנן
דרתיחי עלי. Yadana berabanan derisichi alai.
Okay, so here again maybe a little bit what you were saying.
I know the rabbis are angry at me. And רש"י Rashi says
the reason they're angry at me is because I agreed to be
this policeman. Okay. ולא מיעסקי בי שפיר Velo miaski bi shapir
and they will not attend to me properly in terms of my
burial. You know, they won't show me the proper כבוד. kavod. I
mean obviously they'll bury me, but they'll bury me in a way
that's not fitting. Okay. אוגני בעלייתי, Ogni bi'aliyasi, go ahead and like
lay me down in the, you know, up in the second story,
in the attic. ולא תדחלי מינאי Velo tidcheli minai and don't be
afraid from me like that, you know, that I'll rot or that,
you know, bad things will happen as a result of that. אמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני, Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani, אישתעי לי אימיה
דרבי יונתן, ishtei li imei deRabbi Yonasan,
the mother of רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan told me, דאשתעי לדביתהו דרבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון, de'ishtai lidvasai deRabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon, that רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון's Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon wife, the one who was putting
him in the attic, told her. Okay, so I have it through
his wife, through רבי יונתן's Rabbi Yonasan mother, through רבי יונתן. Rabbi
Yonasan. This is the story I have. לא פחות מתמני סרי, Lo
pachos mitamni srei, no less than eighteen years, ולא טפי מעשרין ותרתי
שנין, velo tfei me'esrin veta rtei shanin, no more than twenty-two years,
אוגניסיה בעלייתא, ognisei bi'aliyasa,
I laid him down up there in the upper chamber. כי הוי
סלקנא מאיננא ליה, Ki havai salikna m'ayna lei, and when I would
go up from time to time to check in on his body,
במזי מאיננא ליה, bimazi mayna lei,
I would look at his hair, כי הוי משתמטא בינתא. ki havai
mishtamta binasa. מיניה minei
when one hair would fall out of his, would fall from his
body, so הוי אתי דמא hava ati dama blood would come out
from the place the hair had fallen, which means like he was
still, his body was still preserved in its original state and there
was still all that blood going on because he apparently according to
this story, it's because he was afraid that he would not be
shown the proper honor in the burial, so better to not be
buried. I don't really get it. Let's get to the end of
the story, okay? יומא חד חזי ריחשא דקנפיק מאוניה yoma chad chaza
richasha dekanaphic me'unei one day I saw like a worm coming out
of his ear. חלש דעתאי chalash daitai I felt very despondent, said
oh my God, his body, something bad is happening to his body,
it isn't being totally preserved. אתחזי לי בחלמא itchazi li becheilma he
appeared to me in a dream, ואמר לי v'amar li and said
to me, לא מידי הוא lo midi hu don't worry, it's nothing.
Here's why it's happening. יומא חד אשמעיה בזילותא דצורבא מרבנן yoma chad
ashmia bizilusa de'chubra me'rabanan one day I heard somebody making
a disparaging a student of the rabbis, ולא מחאי v'lo mchai and
I did not protest and protect his honor. So therefore this punishment
is happening that this worm is coming from my ear. כדבעי ליה
kidevayei lei actually I did protest, but I didn't protest as was
appropriate, the right
degree. כי הוו אתו בי תרי לדינא ki hava asei bei trei
ledina
now, when two people would come for a judgment, how would they,
so they would get Rabbi Eleazar ב'רבי שמעון, b'Rabbi Shimon, who was
dead and lying in the attic, to be their judge. How would
he get them to be their judge? Here's what they would do.
הוו קיימי אפבא hava kamei apaba they would stand by the door,
אמר מר מילתא amar mar milseih one would say here's my side
of the story, ומר מילתא umar milseih the other one would say
his side of the story. נפיק קלא מעיליתא naphiq qala me'iliyasa and
a voice would come out from the upper chamber where his body
was lying, ואמר איש פלוני אתה חייב איש פלוני אתה זכאי v'amar
ish ploni atah chayav ish ploni atah zakai and would give the
פסק. psak. I have no idea what to make of this whole
story. יומא חד yoma chad so anyway, there he was lying in
the upper chamber,
still פסקנינג paskening for people. יומא חד הוה קא מנציא דביתהו בהדי
שיבבתא yoma chad hava kamintaza dabashaiyhu bahadei shivatah
one day his wife was arguing with the neighbor. אמרה לה amra
lah the neighbor said to her, תהא כבעלה שלא ניתן לקבורה tehei
keva'ala shelo nitan le'kvura you just go like to be like your
husband, never to be buried. So אמרו רבנן the rabbis said, כולי
האי ודאי לאו אורח
ארעא kulei hai vadai lav orech ara now clearly it is not
דרך ארץ derech eretz people are sort of now saying this as
a punishment rather than as a נס nes that his body is
preserved, they're saying look, he's not being allowed to be buried. So
now obviously even if he was afraid that the rabbis wouldn't treat
his burial properly, obviously we have to bury him. Okay. איכא דאמרי
רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אתחזי להו בחלמא ika d'amri Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai itchazi lehu becheilma and some say that what happened was Rabbi
שמעון בר יוחאי Shimon bar Yochai appeared to the rabbis in a
dream, and this is Rabbi אלעזר ב'רבי שמעון, Eleazar b'Rabbi Shimon, so
the Rabbi Shimon is Rabbi שמעון בר יוחאי, Shimon bar Yochai, he's
the son of Rabbi שמעון בר יוחאי. Shimon bar Yochai. So Rabbi
שמעון בר יוחאי Shimon bar Yochai appeared to the rabbis in a
dream, ואמר להו v'amar lehu and he said to the rabbis, פרידה
אחת יש לי ביניכם peirada achas yesh li beineichem I have one
dove among you, my son is dwelling there among you, right? ואי
אתם רוצים להביאה אצלי v'ee attem rotzim le'havi'ah eitzli you don't want
to bring him to me up in heaven? You're keeping him from
being buried. So it was time to get him buried. אזלו רבנן
לעסוקי ביה azlu rabanan le'asukei bei the rabbis went up to take
care of him, to begin the burial proceedings. לא שבקו בני עכברייא
lo shavku bnei achvairaya
so the people of the town he was living in, Akhbaraya, did
not let them go to take his body to bury it. דכל
שני דהוה דמיך רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון בעליתא de'kol shanei de'damich Rabbi
Eliezer be'rabbi Shimon be'iliyasa all the years that he was, it's an
interesting verb here, sleeping in the attic, lying, but sleeping in the
attic, לא סלי חיה למתייהו lo sali chaya le'masayehu no bad animal
ever came to their village, so they didn't want him to be
buried, he was protecting their village. יומא חד מעלי יומא דכיפורי הוה
yoma chad malei yoma d'kippuri hava
one day it was ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, הוו טרידי
hava tridi
and then they were all busy in getting ready for יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and eating, I guess. שדרו רבנן shadru rabanan so they
saw they had a window of opportunity, so the rabbis sent בני
בירי bnei biri the people of Biri, which was a neighboring village,
דאסקיה לערסיה de'askiya le'arseih and they went up and they took his
bier, his bed, ואמטיוה למערתא דאבוה v'amtyua le'me'arata d'avuha
and they brought him to the cave of his father where his
father was buried, Rabbi שמעון בר יוחאי. Shimon bar Yochai. אשכחו עכנא
ashkachu achana they found a serpent דהדר לה למערתא da'adar lehu le'me'arata
that was circling in front of the opening of the cave, wouldn't
let them in. רש"י Rashi describes this as the serpent that like
is swallowing its tail. אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him,
עכנא עכנא achana achana serpent, serpent, פתח פיך pishach picha open your
mouth, right, which is let the tail fall off and open up
the space, ויכנס ברא אצל אביו v'yikanas beira eitzel aviv and let
the son come in and be with his father. פתח להו pachach
lehu he opened up. שלח רבי shlach rebbi okay, so that's now
he got buried. Now that he's buried, we're just going to read
just another minute, got to finish the story. Now that he's buried,
so remember Rebbi was the one who was complaining about his wife,
especially if you read the story back about this wicked woman, look
at all this procreation that she prevented. Now that he's buried, שלח
רבי לדבר באשה shlach rebbi le'dabair be'ishah
Rebbi wanted to go ahead and have somebody speak on his behalf
to his wife, wanted to actually now marry the widow, okay, which
he might have been talking about earlier. שלחה ליה shlacha lei so
she sent back to him, כלי שנשתמש בו קודש ישתמש בו חול
kli she'nishtamesh bo kodesh yishtamesh bo chol
a vessel that was used for somebody holy should now be used
for something profane? So this is she telling to Rabbi יהודה הנשיא
Yehuda Hanasi this way, right? תמן אמרין, taman amrin, there we say,
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the similar saying they have for this
is: באתר דמרי ביתא תלא זייניה, be-asar demarei beisa tala zainei, in
the same peg that the master of the house hung his weapons,
כוביא רעיא קולסיה תלא, kuba raya kulsei tala, should the shepherd hang
his like, you know, his wallet, you know, his pouch? So it
says a little more a little more sexual imagery, I think. Anyway,
so basically she said, no thank you. Okay. שלח לה, shlach lah,
so he sent to her,
look, maybe he was greater than me in תורה, but במעשים טובים
be-maasim tovim
is he greater than me? I mean, I'm רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rebbe
Yehuda HaNasi, I supply, you know, I provide for people, I'm wealthy,
I do all these things, I, you know, I'm the, you know,
I take I'm the head of the Jewish, you know, you know,
whatever, I devote myself to the public good. So שלחה ליה, shalcha
lei, she said back to him: בתורה מיהא גדול ממך, be-Torah miya
gadol mimcha, first of all, you just admitted that he's greater than
you in תורה, number one. לא ידענא, I didn't know that, but
you yourself had just now admitted to that. But but if you
want to talk about מעשים טובים, maasim tovim, במעשה ידענא, be-maise yadana,
I actually know that he was greater than you in מעשים טובים.
maasim tovim. Why? דקביל עליה יסורי, de-kibil alei yisurei,
that he accepted on him on himself יסורים. yisurim. Now I don't
know why accepting upon yourself afflictions means you're greater, maybe greater in
your own personal character that you're willing to suffer. I don't know
it means מעשים טובים maasim tovim in terms of helping other people.
Okay. And
you know what? It's already very late, so we'll end here even
though we're not totally done, but we will continue here with the
story about רבי trying to marry רבי אלעזר בר שמעון's Rebbe Elazar
bar Shimon wife.